# 你看 下雨 全部都圍在這裡
Look! It's raining and they're all gathering here.
# 笑一下
Show me your smile!
# 那狗會笑的 它不笑了現在 快點笑一下
That dog smiles a lot, but he's not smiling now. C'mon! Show me your smile!
# 笑一下我給塊肉給你吃
Show me your smile and you can get a piece of meat from me.
# 你看 它看著我吃辣條哦
Look! She's watching me eating latiao (lit: spicy strip, a kind of snack)
# 要不要辣條
Do you want latiao?
# 很辣的哦
It's really spicy, you know.
# 你不吃的
You won't like it.
# 你快要嗎 小狗
And you want it too? Puppy
# 現在下雨啊 那狗都是 在這邊上 (註︰這個「邊」不知怎釋，就是們前的一級而已)
It's raining now. The dogs are, all here on this step.
# 一地都是狗
Dogs are everywhere.
# 現在小狗都送的差不多啦 還有七八條
Now I've given out almost all puppies, except seven or eight of them.
# 等下我又送兩條給我的那個
Later today I'll give another two to my, you know,
# 給我親戚
to my relatives.
# 放在它家養 把它養大
They'll keep the puppies, and raise them up.
# 送一條公的跟一條母的給他們
I'm gonna give them a boy and a girl.
# 太多啦
Here are too many dogs.
# 小黑
Blacky!
# 哪個是小黑
Which one is Blacky?
# 小黑肯定跟到我
Blacky must have gone to my,
# 我老家去啦
to my home.
# 我老家有點
At my home, there's some,
# 有點那個剩飯
some sort of leftover.
# 它跑去 跑回去吃啦
So she's, she's having a feast there.
# 嗯
Um!
# 嗯 昨天跑回來那狗嘞
Um? Where's the dogs that came back yesterday?
# 昨天流浪了一個禮拜的那狗不知道跑哪裡去了 (註︰這句他說得有點亂)
The dog had been straying for a week. He came back yesterday. But he's gone again.
# 一個禮拜都不見它 今天居然回來啦 (註︰那究竟是昨天還是今天回來的....)
He has disappeared for one whole week. But he's back today.
# 現在 餓的它皮包骨一樣
Now, he was starving and he's now like a skeleton.
# 誒 走到哪裡去啦
Eh? Where is he now?
# 小黑過來 (註︰這其實不是小黑)
Come here, Little Black!
# 你看就這個
Look! It's this one.
# 這狗 你看 瘦的都不成樣子了
This dog, look! He's now ridiculously skinny.
# 離家出走了一個禮拜
He has run away for a week.
# 現在才回來
And now he's back, after one whole week.
# 看都變色了
His coat has already discoloured.
# 你看 是不是 (註︰是不是甚麼呢....)
Look! Am I right?
# 這隻跟了我 一直跟著我的
This one has been with me... It's always with me.
# 這個就不聽話 跑到外面去
This one is naughty. He ran outside,
# 跟豬跑了
with the pigs,
# 跟那大公豬 上山上去玩
with the big boar. They had fun on the hill.
# 你看 現在都回來了發抖 再不回來的話可能就
Look! He's now back and is trembling. If he stays any longer outside,
# 會
then,
# 永遠永遠都回不來了
he might never, never be able to come back.
# 剛剛吃飽 你看
He has just had a big meal. Look!
# 肚子都吃那麼大了
His stomach is getting that big now!
# 你敢不敢跑啦 你跟著豬跑 是不是
Dare you run away again? You ran out with the pigs, didn't you?
# 在家都不好好待著
You didn't stay at home like a good boy.
# 還跟它走
But you ran away with the boar.
# 你看
Look!
# 餓的不現在剩下皮包骨啦
You were starving and you're now not so much different from a skeleton.
# 現在腳都發抖
Now his legs are trembling.
# 沒事的 過兩天就好了
No worries. He'll fine in a couple of days.
# 那公豬也不知道跑哪裡去了 公豬
The boar has run away to somewhere only god knows, the boar.
# 這裡還受傷了 這裡
Here's even a wound, here.
# 我今天給它摘了 摘了點葯水
I've put on some, some medication on him today.
# 給了點碘伏給它擦了下 (註︰是他自己說拿給狗的，我照譯而已)
I gave him some povidone-iodine.
# 很快就會好了
He'll get well very soon.
# 這就是你看 這個跟 跟著我的狗
And this is, look! This is the, the dog which has always been with me.
# 是不是
Am I right?
# 雖然 雖 雖然伙食不是很好
Although, al, although you don't have any excess here,
# 但是溫飽還是沒問題的 哦
but you never starve, right?
# 現在好肥了
You're already very fat.
# 不能吃 少吃一點 知不知道
You can't eat, eat less! Got it?
# 太肥了不好看的
You're not cute anymore if you get too fat.
# 好好摸 它這個狗頭
It feels really great, touching his dog head.
# 現在的牙齒都長得好利啦 就它最兇 專門欺負小狗
Now his teeth are really sharp. He's the most fierce and always bullies other puppies.
# 是不是
Am I right?
# 最兇的就是你
You're the most fierce.
# 笑 笑
Smile! Smile!
# 它不笑
He doesn't smile.
# 笑不出來是不是
You just can't smile, right?
# 要不要骨頭吃
Do you want some bones?
# 昨天 昨天我搞了一大盆骨頭給它們吃
Yesterday, yesterday I gave them a huge plate of bones.
# 一口氣
Immediately,
# 一分鐘都不用 全部吃完啦
in less than a minute, all were gone.
# 這個毛 太多啦
His fur, he has too much.
# 一身的毛都崩起來
His fur is curling up all over the body.
# 幹嘛 上次我都 打過你 你都不聽話
What do you want? Last time I, I beat you, cuz you were naughty.
# 去咬人家的雞 是不是
You bit other people's chickens, didn't you?
# 你去咬人家被我打了一次 現在又那麼
You bit others and I beat you. And now you're so,
# 還那麼
you're still so,
# 還那麼喜歡跟我黏在一起
you still enjoy that much getting attached to me.
# 不聽話就要打 知不知道
You deserved it cuz you were naughty. Got it?
# 你看 它現在
Look! Now she,
# 乖的很
she's such a good girl.
# 可能害怕我 我鞭它
Perhaps she's scared, that I might flog her.
# 所以它一直 一直在
So she's now trying, trying to,
# 靠近我 是不是
get close to me, am I right?
# 是不是 肯定 它肯定想靠近我
Right? Surely, surely she wants to get close to me,
# 跟我 和好
and reconcile with me.
# 這樣才是 好狗
That's exactly how a, good dog, should be.
# 對主人那麼忠誠 是不是
You're so loyal to your master, aren't you?
# 不要去咬人家的雞 知不知道
You shouldn't bite their chickens. Got it?
# 咬人家的雞的話 人家會罵的
You would be scolded if you do.
# 人家養雞也不容易呀
Not to say that raising the chickens is never an easy task.
# 誒 是不是你
Eh? Is that you?
# 你也跟著去了 是不是
You followed her, didn't you?
# 這個 這個腳都是白的
Her, her feet are white.
# 這裡也是白的 嘿嘿
She's also white here, hehe!
# 它們很喜歡我這樣拎著它
They like it so much when I'm holding them here.
# 還有一條 這個 小花狗
One more, this is, tinted puppy.
# 小花狗你給我過來 小花狗 就你不聽話 你看
Tinted, you come here, you tinted puppy. You're always the naughty one. Look!
# 就它不老實
He's never a good boy.
# 我不把它它就en~en~的叫
Whenever I hold him, he always yelps like "en~en~".
# 是不是
Am I right?
# 看它肚子 看到沒有 小肚子
Have a look at his tummy. See? Little tummy.
# 小肚腩 吃飽啦
Little belly. He's eaten a lot.
# 你看一下送哪 哪兩條給
Let me see which one, which two should I give,
# 給我家那個
to my, you know,
# 我家姑姑
my aunt.
# 隨便挑兩條就好啦
Whichever two. It doesn't matter.
# 反正這條不送給別人
And this one is never on the list. I'm not giving him to anyone.
# 這條我就把你養大
This one, I'll bring you up.
# 誒呀
Eya!
# 你看
Look!
# 哦
Oh!
# 看 看能不能頂得住我
See, see if you can stand my weight.
# 我才九十斤
I'm only forty-five kilograms.
# 哼哼 騙它的
Hm hm, I'm just kidding.
# 誒
Ey!
# 不行 大瘦小了 我又不敢用力坐
No no. She's too weak and skinny. I dare not give her my full weight.
# 你怎麼那麼可愛
How can you be that cute?
# 我就不送你了啊 嘖
So I'm not giving you to anyone, okay?
# 送其它那幾條 隨便找兩條去
I'll choose from the others. Any two would be fine.
# 送兩條給他們
I'll give them two.
# 現在壓力大呀
Life is not easy these days.
# 養不起它們啦 要慢慢地把它送掉一些
I can't afford keeping them all. I need to give out some of them.
# 剩下的
And the rest,
# 剩下的就
the rest will be,
# 大狗就留下來吧
the big dogs will be staying here.
# 小狗 幾乎要把它送走
But puppies, almost all will be given out.
# 不然養不起呀 太多啦
Otherwise I can't afford. Here are too many dogs.
# 就是這一條 一條生了那麼多
It used to be just one dog. All other dogs came from her.
# 就它
Here she is.
# 你看
Look!
# 做奶奶咯
You're now a grandma.
# 好啦好啦好啦好啦 你們到外面玩啊
Alright, alright, alright, alright! Enjoy your time outside, okay?
# 這裡面不適合你們
You won't feel great here inside.
# 現在狗崽越來越少啦
Now, we have less and less puppies here.
# 我一條條把它送出去
I'm giving them out, one after the other.
# 不要那麼多
I don't need so many.
# 抓 抓都抓不住
I, I couldn't even touch it.
# 快點過來
Come here!
# (狗狗狗狗狗狗狗狗) (註︰沒有原字幕)
Puppies, puppies, puppies!
# (狗)
Puppies!
# 想抓一條都抓不到了
I can't catch even one.
# 全部不願意去
They're not willing to leave.
# 這裡那麼好哇
Here is such a good place, isn't it?
# 沒辦法啊 養不起你們啦
I have no choice. I can't afford keeping you all.
# (狗狗狗狗狗狗狗狗)
Puppies, puppies, puppies
# (狗)
Puppies!
# 我偷襲它
Let me attack from the back.
# 它咬人的
He bites!
# 那麼小就咬人
You're still a kid, but you bite!
# 這怎麼行 這麼兇
How can it be? You're so fierce.
# 嗯 這個個乖啦 (註︰這小狗是公的，但後面知道他一直以為這是母的，所以用"She")
Um! This is a very good girl.
# 走 帶你去玩
Let's go, and have some fun!
# 去不去
Are you going?
# 你看這個
Look! She's,
# 那麼大啦
already that big now.
# 把這個蓋起來
Let me cover it up.
# 蓋下它就跑不出來
Cover it up and then she can't run away.
# 還要抓一條
I need to catch one more.
# (狗)
Puppy!
# 都不肯
They don't want it!
# 這裡有一條 這 有一條黑的
Here's one. Here's, a black one.
# (狗狗)
Puppies, puppies!
# (狗)
Puppies!
# 那麼不聽話
So naughty!
# 上來了
He gets up!
# 你看 就抓了這兩條
Look! So I've caught these two.
# 抓這兩條
So I'll give these two,
# 送給我大姑家
to my aunt.
# 現在我們把它送上去
We're gonna send them there now.
# 現在都有十來斤啦
I think they're nearly ten kilograms now.
# 快養不起它們啦
They'll soon eat up all my money.
# 送掉
So, given them out!
# 一條條的送
One after the other!
# 不知道怎麼弄
But how can I make it?
# 有沒有蓋子
Is there a cover?
# 可以 反過來
Alright! Turn it over!
# 好兇呀 它們
They're so fierce!
# 把它 放進來
Put them, inside.
# 可以 這樣 這樣抬著
Alright! Then, then I can take it.
# 狗崽子 哈哈
Puppies, haha
# 拿過去
Put them there
# 呃 出來
Eh! Come out!
# 這是你們的新家啦
This is your new home.
# 這條 這條很靚哦
This one, this one is beautiful, isn't it?
# 嗯
Yup!
# 吃了很飽啦
He's eaten a lot
# 兩條都是公狗嗎
Are they both boys?
# 不是吧
No, it shouldn't be.
# 看一下來
Let me check.
# 母狗吧 這條
This is should be a girl, this one.
# 母狗還是公狗
Is it a girl or a boy?
# 跑雞窩裡面去了
She's getting into the roost.
# 母狗還是公狗
A girl or a boy?
# 你看 它們就住在這裡 這裡比那裡好多啦
Look! So they are staying here now. Here is much better than there.
# 乾淨多了
It's so much cleaner.
# 一下就很適應了這裡的環境
They've already get used to this place.
# 你看 不哭也不鬧
Not crying, nor yelping.
# 在這裡
They're looking for food,
# 找東西吃
here and there.
# 這要過段時間 不敢放哦
I dare not take them out. Perhaps later.
# 不能放 過兩天就可以啦
No, you shouldn't now. But it'll be fine in a couple of days.
# 你看 它在找東西吃了
Look! He's looking for food.
# 這個就是你他的新家啦
From now on, this is your new home.
# 嘖 你看 一看就是大戶人家
Look! I can tell immediately that this is a wealthy family.
# 牆都貼瓷板啦
They even have porcelain tiles on the wall.
# 一點都不陌生哦
It doesn't seem to be a new place to him at all.
# 好啦 我們準備回去啦
Alright! We're getting ready to go back.
# 下次我們再來看它們
We'll come again to see them next time.